[Music]
Welcome to the busy central launch
edition 2025 release wave 2. My name is
Alexander Totoich and I would like to
present new functionality in a busy
central excise tax framework. I just
wanted to remind you this edition will
deliver this as a framework. So we will
not cover specific excise tax
calculations but even in this situation
I want to emphasize business value of
this investment and what will come in
the future. So with excess taxes
calculation you can expect in the future
different type of excess tax
calculations. We will provide uh
regulatory accuracy and compliance with
many different uh requirements. So it
will definitely minimize risk on
penalties make it easier especially in
operation efficiency. You can easily
calculate based on existing information
in the system. So it will be important
for the future usage. What is about?
You can find excise tax uh journal and
when you are there
uh you can find what is important in
excise journal batch you will see
different types of u option you can use.
As I said for the beginning we will be
focus on what is inside. So we have
excise journal, we have extra journal
template and batch. So this is where you
will enter your information or where you
calculate and uh collect all information
and once when you register when you post
because not posting because we will
register you will have excise taxes
registration transaction logs.
Okay, this is completely extendable. So
not only for real excise taxes. This is
important. Even the name uh make
assumption that is only for regular
excess taxes not for all. So all taxes
based on similar sources. So in the
future it can be used for plastic tax
for sugar tax for many similar uh things
but calculated the same way as safe
taxes. In this edition as I said it is
delivered as a framework but in
sustainability uh option we introduce
CBM and EPR calculation on a top of this
framework. So we have two options in in
this release but not related direct with
excise taxes with CBM and EPR. As you
can see on this slide when you go to
type you have first option CBM EPR and
excises.
uh based on what option you choose, you
can uh have different uh field option on
a journal. So let's look in a demo what
is there. We will have different session
about CBM and EPR. So I'm uh inviting
you to watch another session so you can
see what is built on the top of this
framework. So now I just wanted to show
you basic framework. This is excise
journal and in this excise journal you
can have a option to see that these
excise calculations can be based on
purchase on sales documents. So in some
situation you will track on a purchase
on some situation on sales. So even if
this is manufacturing you can easily
extend and use different sources for
calculation. Once when you choose then
you can collect information from
different entities. The most of cases it
will be item because item is unique
place where you can configure uh
calculation uh for different excise
taxes and when we talk what is actually
there why we call this excise because
there are all taxes not related for
financial data but related to maybe to
weight or volume or specific quantity.
So you can easily connect uh specific
tax or x size to sum of unit of measure
or other uh values on item cards. But
not only items you can connect resources
with item charge other options for fixed
assets depends from country to country
how it can be treated as a excise tax
one you will choose for example item you
can have here you can see what is a
quantity so in this moment for non CBM
and EPR options if you want to use you
have two options you can manually
populate information based on some other
sources and probably you will not do it
or you can build your own calculation
uh as extension of this framework but
definitely uh we can promise we will
enable some additional option for excise
taxes in a future releases. We want to
get your feedback what is the most
important for you and we will go this
way.
Okay. Now before I close this session I
want to remind you about general
business central resources. You have all
these links actually six links. So
please use them. You can find many
different and many important resources
there. Do not forget subscribe our
LinkedIn channel because you can follow
all our weekly and news and
announcements. And the last but not the
least our YouTube channel. You can find
this video there but other videos from
this edition and from previous edition.
So remember AKMSBC YouTube.
So thank you for watching this session.